This task has a rather long task
description which is split into two parts.
The first part is more general notes and
the second part contains the actual task.
The remarks within the first part are that
these lines here are required in Autotool, but
they should be removed if you test locally.
So you can delete these lines
or you can comment them out.
So this is what I do.
I comment out these lines and of
course if you have a task uploaded
to Autotool, that task should contain exactly
these lines or more or less exactly these lines.
We can use any function that is defined
here within our task as well as 'return'.
This given set of functions and 'return' are
the IO functions that we are allowed to use.
Otherwise, Autotool could reject the task.
Then there are some more general notes for
some systems specifically, for instance, here:
If you somehow could not execute this
task, you can add an import which
will then allow you to use
the functions mentioned above.
So if that's an issue on your machine
you might have to add simply this line.
And another remark is about
hSetBuffering stdout NoBuffering.
This line here – so this is a line you could add
in your program if it's not
running for you on your machine.
I add this as an additional line.
If you want to be sure not to have
trouble with the issue, then you can
add this line as the first line of your program.
And then afterwards start the actual program.
Now there are remarks on the
program that's to be written.
So these are the remarks for the actual task.
We have to write a program
that reads two integers,
even negative ones, and prints out their sum.
This behavior is repeated until the
first time the first number is zero.
If that's the case, then the program terminates
and prints out the number of additions.
In this case, it's also not
reading a second number.
It's allowed to add additional
information to the output.
So you can modify the output as well and have
more output for the final result or
output for the results of the addition.
So you can have an output which
indicates what's happening there.
And that's also what you should do!
So you should indicate what the user
has to do next and so on and so forth.
The Autotool might give some error messages:
This part is just a description of what
the Autotool may say if your program
is wrong or the Autotool
thinks your task is wrong.
It's the last section here.
But I think we simply ignore
that one here in this case.
I just remove it to have the actual
task description a bit closer by.
Now we have the main program
starting and we want to have actually a program
that runs always until a given number is zero.
So what we want to have is a
function that is recursing somehow.
Using our main program for this
recursion is no good attempt, I think.
Because we want to count and
when we use our main function
there is no possibility to give
a parameter for the counting.
So we're required to have some other
function, and we can name it somehow.
I will just call it countedAdds.
So this is the function that's
called again and again and again.
That asks us to use again and again.
It is using IO, but it also has a parameter
which is the number of current additions.
This (the latter) is an integer value.
This is the function countedAdds
and it has this parameter.
It's an IO function. So I write do here.
Within the main function, we will
call this countedAdds function.
Now we are able to recurse
within the countedAdds function.
What we want to have is, we want
to ask the user for a first number.
That's the first step we have to do.
The task says we have to indicate somehow
to the user what's coming up next.
So we could simply just let
the user input a number.
Let's say readLn which reads
some input and this is a
somehow a value of some type
that we have with this x.
Then we could say if x equals
zero, then we are done.
Then 'do' – we could simply output a
String, for instance, saying 'done'.
And else we could recurse.
So if it's not a zero, then we go
again to countedAdds and increase n.
It's simply increased by one.
I will call this program within ghci.
Here is the advice that
hSetBuffering is not available,
therefore we could use the line we
had before. So import System.IO.
When we use this one and reload
then that's compiling fine.
hSetBuffering is within System.IO and if we
have this available then our program will run.
If this is not an issue for you then you
could leave out this line and this line here.
And if you have no issues with executing
the program then you can skip these lines.
Now when I start this program
and we just have this read
line here then we do not get any interaction.
It's rather just the program asking us for
a number but not giving an output for it.
So we would have to guess what's happening now.
And if we answer zero then the
program is terminating but if we
do not then the program runs until we enter zero.
Well, it's not the complete
program that we want to implement.
This is rather just an implementation
just demonstrating what's happening here.
We want to have an output
for what's happening here.
We want it to ask the user to do something.
So we can use putStr for this.
We can then type a message as a
string – this will be printed out.
We can say "first number or 0 for exit".
This is what the user has to do.
So he now will have some
information about what's happening.
If we reload the program then our
user will see what's happening here.
This is the simple output
we had here with putStr.
Some of you might have used print instead of
putStr but you should not use print
because then your output is somehow weird.
Because then you have your string printed
as a string which somehow looks very funny.
You should use putStr rather than
print, this just as a side remark.
Now we are already getting one number but
actually we're required to have two numbers.
This is the else case in which
we want to have a second number.
Let's program this part here.
Again we want to have the
user know what's happening.
We want to give him a message that
he has to insert a second number.
So we ask him for a second number and again we
can use readLn in order to get a second number.
We use the left arrow in order to give it a name.
This value will be within y.
Now we can give a message
of what's happening next.
Next we shall print the
number, that's the sum.
We shall print out the sum of these two numbers.
We can say a message like – also you put
use putStr for this one – "The sum of".
Now we can add the actual Int
values here – of x and y.
We can say the sum of x and y.
We have to use brackets here in
order to combine it to one string.
I use ++ in order to combine
many things into one string.
(x ++)
We want to show x and y and then
print the actual result of the sum.
In this case we have to use show
rather than x and y specifically.
Because x and y shall be integers
we have to use show here in order
to deliver them as strings to the user.
The sum – we can use print for this.
We could also put this into the putStr
so with another ++ but I use print here.
So we can say x + y in order to sum them up.
Otherwise if I hadn't used
print I would have to use show.
So ++ show and x + y so it's a bit longer
- so this is the short version here.
After this we continue with our loop.
That's basically the major part of the program.
What's missing? –
Well let's execute this part.
So that we can see it.
Let's load it.
We give a first number.
Let's say -9 and the second
number is 8. Their sum is -1.
If we add 2 and 3 that's 5, if we add 5 and 0
that's 5, and if we take 0 then we are done.
So what's missing?
Well the program terminates – not reading a
second number – that's what's happening already,
but printing the number of additions performed!
We haven't had the output of
the additions that happened.
I already increased the counter.
We have a counter of zero here and we have
increased this counter with
every run of countedAdds.
So the only thing that's missing
is using the n in order to show
the output of the result of these adds.
What we can do is: we can inform the
user that the program is terminating.
I use this putStrLn here.
When we are done and it says
"Done. Exiting the program."
Then I want to print the number
of additions that happened.
Again I want to tell the user what's happening.
So: the number of additions
performed was – and then the number.
Again I use print here in this case.
We can use print n in order to print
the number of additions that happened.
If I reload the program and run
it, then when we are done now.
Let's say 4, 5, 9, 7, and 0.
Then we see we have two times first numbers and
two times second numbers and the output is 2.
If we run the program again
and we give as first input 9
and as second input 0 and then a 0, then we get
just 1 as the number of performed additions.
If we leave the program immediately, we get 0,
so this is the number of additions
that happened during our program run.
There are other ways of expressing
reading the number of integers.
We could also read strings and
convert them into integers.
This would be another approach.
Instead of getting x as read
we could use getLine here.
But in this case we can't use x
in order to compare it with 0,
because then we get a type error.
Because x is the string and so there is
nothing to compare for strings with numbers.
But we can fix this by saying x' is an Integer.
And this integer we get by reading x.
So instead of readLn we can use
getLine and read afterwards.
Then we can use x' here which is the x we read.
Then we can run the program as well and just
to show you – the program is still running.
Actually we see it because it's
compiling but we can execute it as well.
And another point here is: if we have this
hSetBuffering here then we
should have the do above here.
But if we do not have the hSetBuffering here we
can omit the do and simply call countedAdds here.
This is just a simplification
of the program which
you should do if there's just
a single line after the do.
Now we are done also with
the cosmetics of the program.
There are other ways of expressing stuff.
As I showed with getLine
and read instead of readLn.
Also for printing the output
there are different functions.
putStrLn prints the string
and the new line afterwards.
putStr prints the string without a new line.
That's why we get this prompt here with
asking for a number within the same line.
If we choose putStrLn, then we get a prompt where
– oh I forgot to reload –
If we do this, then we get a prompt
where the cursor is on the next line.
And we enter the number on the next line.
So that's the difference there.
For strings we should use putStr or putStrLn.
And for other values we use print but we should
not use print for Strings because otherwise
we get also delimitation
characters for the string.
When we get them that's not such a nice output.
Okay, and that's it for this task.